to get in. So, uh, we are admitting
everybody now. Good afternoon everyone
as people are joining into the meeting.
Uh, just as a re couple of reminders, my
name is Dominic Zerllo and I'm with the
Department of Health and I'm here to
help uh with regard to uh making sure
the committee meeting itself continues
to move forward well. Um and um uh just
as a reminder because we do record these
meetings and the recording has started,
we do ask that people watch uh and use
appropriate language during the meeting
simply because we do want to be able to
post it up on our website. And
occasionally if people are using
language that's not appropriate for all
ages, uh it can delay in us being able
to post it as we have to edit it at that
point. and we would rather not edit and
just have things as they are presented.
Um, and then uh that's also part of the
reason why we do not have cameras on for
everyone. Um, and there's two reasons
for that. One again to make sure that
everything is appropriate in the video.
And um, and the second one is because we
have so many people who participate from
other portions of the state that do not
necessarily always have the greatest
internet access. um the video
unfortunately takes up a lot of
bandwidth and causes people to drop off
of the meeting and have to rejoin and
that does happen sometimes now anyway.
We just try to minimize it and so I uh
so we try to keep only a few people with
videos on um and so with that I will
turn this on over uh this is the end of
life care committee and the chair of it
is uh Dr. Larry Leman and so uh Dr. Dr.
Leman, I will turn it on over to you.
>> Great. Thanks. Thank Thank you, Dom. Um,
great to see we have a nice big crowd
today. I thank everybody for coming here
and participating. Um, before we start,
um, I want to just go over a little bit
of a a potential model for for our next
few meetings and our next process. So
this meeting, you know, in a minute I'll
introduce Jen Clement, who's a thought
leader in end of life and a psychedelic
chaplain who's going to talk about some
of the role of spirituality in end of
life care. Um for our next meeting um
which is tenatively planned for the 20th
um Danielle our our death doula who's
actually on the call is going to talk
about the role of um psychedelic death
doulas. And then for April 3, uh um uh
Jim Brown, James Brown will be talking
about issues of pharmarmacology that
apply to um you know, end of end of life
care. So we sort of have three meetings
where we're covering each of those
areas. I want to just put a call out if
you know I'm sure there's things maybe
I'm we're not thinking about. If there's
someone else that should come, you know,
come talk to us, um you know, please
share that with me either in the chat
now or or personally. I have thought
about um if we could invite somebody
from DA or PBLO person who may want to
talk about um relevance to working like
culturally with um um end of life care.
the after those three meetings, my hope
is that we've had a lot of interest in
having a blended meeting um where we uh
where people can be in person and have a
conversation. Um actually there at the
same time though it would be blended so
people online would be able to watch and
contribute. So I think we'll work on
that for potentially like end of April
sort of timing there. More or less
looking for like averaging about every
three weeks on meetings. So you'll see
we have a four-week break here and then
we have them every every other week for
a while.
So um the format today is going to be um
Jen Kmente who is our uh thought leader
in u psychedelic end of life care um is
going to share her presentation um which
I think is about a 25m minute
presentation 30 minutes and then we're
just going to have an open discussion
well first we'll have questions that are
directed to Jen and then an open open
discussion on different issues that have
come up. So, Jen, thank you so much. We
really totally appreciate your
volunteering to to be here and I've had
a little peek at your presentation. It's
quite quite interesting and exciting.
So, thank you.
>> Thank you. Should I go ahead and share?
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> Okay. Let's see if I could do this.
Share this window.
Okay. Do you see it?
>> Yes, we do, Jen.
>> Okay, great.
So I'm calling this a framework for end
of life care within the medical
psilocybin program. And for me when I'm
thinking about New Mexico, I think of
shiprock when I think of spiritual care
and spirituality and sacred places. So I
tried to represent uh shiprock in this
uh in this in this presentation. So
those of you who've been to Shiprock uh
tell me if I got it right or tell me if
AI got it right.
And do you see just my presentation
right now or do you see my notes as
well?
>> Uh right now just seeing the framework
for end of life image.
>> Okay, great. Okay, wonderful.
>> Well, so I just wanted to start out by
saying, you know, I've had the honor to
spend a lot of time on this topic over
the past few weeks and probably over the
past few years as well, but most most
concentrated in the last few weeks. And
you know, I've had a chance to hear from
a lot of people on this in this um this
realm, this nexus of spiritual care,
chapency, and psychedelics. Um some of
some of whom I believe have joined us
today. I can't see who's here, but um I
trust that some of the folks I've been
speaking with have joined. So, thank you
if you have. And so I want to just kind
of start by saying that, you know,
despite my attempt to gather all these
inputs and present a a a fair portrayal
of where this area is currently and
where we might go, I wanted to disclose
that my process of creating this
presentation was really based on um many
of my own questions. And I kind of
imagine many of you are asking the same
ones such as like, you know, where do I
fit in with my skill set and expertise
or u my desire to have skill set and
expertise? ultimately, how may I serve
this population? And am I prepared? Um,
and then most importantly, what
additional training and experience do I
need? And I know that's a question
that's um being answered by possibly
another committee, but I think it's fair
for us to start asking these questions.
So as the committee really refineses
this act and has these conversations, I
would encourage uh clarity um getting
clear around the interdisciplinary roles
um the scope the aligning of the scope
and the pathways that we need to build
that ensure that existential suffering
isn't overlooked because it doesn't fit
in this you know little diagnostic box.
So our goals should be you know three
dignity safety or four of them access
dignity safety and and integrated care
that aren't like a restricted by having
integrated or regulatory silos.
So where I want to start here I I think
a good place to start is um looking at
Dame Sicily Saunders definition of total
pain. Um and you know this did really
reframe pain management from you know
just merely symptom control to um
meaning centered care. Um I think she
she created this definition in the 60s.
She's the founder of the modern hospice
movement for those of you who don't know
which I'm sure everybody here does. Um
so this area this idea of total pain
really I think legitimized the roles of
chaplain as well as you know social
workers and anybody in that
interdisciplinary team that works
alongside the medical team the medical
uh roles and this is kind of informing
you know spiritual care the contemporary
approach to you know existential
assessment ethical accompanyment and
today I I really believe it's supporting
this emerging discussion around
psychedelic assisted palative care so um
you know Under the medical psilocybin
act, end of life distress is explicitly
included as a qualifying condition and
that's that's why we've been meeting um
and this really positions the state as a
national leader in acknowledging
existential suff suffering as a
legitimate medical concern. So it also
creates that imperative to facilitate
medically supervised experiences that
are capable of surfacing these profound
questions of you know meaning and
identity.
So what is spiritual care in psychedelic
medicine? So in the psychedelic context,
you know, people aren't really grappling
only grappling with meaning or belief um
but also being um itself um the nature
of consciousness, non-duality, mortality
and this really comes into focus during
um end of life settings. So the focus is
really around that spiritual,
existential, religious and theological
um concerns or cert um and that that
term emerged as a shared language for
naming spiritual and existential clinic
care in the clinical and quasi clinical
environments. That's what I found out.
Um and then it's all about maintaining
the sacred witness role um non-directive
presence and then supporting experiences
that can't be immediately interpreted or
resolved. So that's kind of a basic you
know kind of framework for spiritual
care and psychedelic medicine. Um so the
term psychedelic chapency um I came
across this gosh I think during during
the pandemic there was a webinar that
Harvard Divinity School put together and
I think um Charles Stang came up with
this term or brought it together and I
was really um it really piqued my
interest and it's just been kind of
building in my mind ever since. So what
it what it really means is it's a form
of professional spiritual care that
supports individuals engaging with
psychedelic experiences by addressing
spiritual, existential, religious,
theological and ontological concerns
that may arise before and after uh these
experiences.
So the the components of this are really
like you know the the meaning making
spiritual assessment um preparation and
integration support um
non-denominational client centric care
and ethical safeguarding against that
meaning and position.
So then we can ask you know why do we
need formal training? I mean a lot of a
lot of us have you know done parts and
pieces of this work. Um there's, you
know, chaplain on one side and there's,
you know, deathdas and other
practitioners on the other. Um and so,
you know, we're kind of trying to figure
out why we need more formal training and
if it's necessary and how do we get it
and so I just wanted to outline some of
the reasons uh why. Um and I think these
things are pretty obvious. Obviously,
during a psychedelic experience, there's
heightened suggestability. Um it's easy
for people to unintentionally impose
meaning. Even if you're wearing a shirt
with like Shiva on it, you know, are you
imposing meaning during a psychedelic
setting. Um the non the complexity of
being non-denominational is real.
There's a lot of different assumptions
that maybe bump up against some
somebody's tradition. So for example, a
Baptist Christian may not have the same
values as a uh um you know, more
contemporary um kind of new age
Christian, for example. Um thirdly, you
know, this is high stakes work. there's
a trauma that can come of it. You know,
somebody could die during an experience
um or have more anxiety around it. There
could be a lot of onlogical shock. Now,
those of us who've been using psychedux
or experience with it have all probably
experienced this before where something
was just, you know, blew our reality
away. And these things can be very much
amplified in end of life or um terminal
illness situations. There's also this
ethical risk. We have a lot of power
differential differentials that can come
up. Um patients are super vulnerable. Um
there's a you know questions around you
know use of touch. Um
uh so and also guru dynamics around you
know the role clarity. So we want to
make sure patients are protected against
those um those potential power issues um
that come up a lot in psychotherapy or
in you know um in religious settings. So
the idea here is that you know without
um role uh without formal training
anybody who's a care provider may
unintent unintentionally exploit any of
these vulnerabilities um at the worst or
you know even just fail to recognize
unmet needs and signs of distress. So if
we have great good training that could
establish clear ethical obligations um
reporting pathways and standards of
care, we could probably do some good in
preventing harm and ensuring our
patients are well protected.
So um this came out of a um a study uh
based on Pitky uh Pitky's work on from
Journal of Psychopharmarmacology in
2024.
So he outlined the uh unadressed
spiritual existential harms in a really
nice easy to understand way. So um these
are the five uh meaning disruption,
identity disturbance, spiritual
bypassing, interpretive imposition and
uh delayed effects. So again you know
avoiding uh engagement with meaning
making um and spiritual impact doesn't
reduce the risk but it could actually
shift harm into unmonitored domains. So
under this framework um the psychedelic
chaplain functions as a kind of
infrastructure
to for ex existential harm reduction and
ethical accountability. So um I would
argue and I I fall on the side of this
that it really makes it necessary by
design rather than optional. And I know
that in the current language of SB219 um
this kind of spiritual care is optional.
So that's one of the questions and
issues I'm raising in this presentation.
So here I wanted to give you a sense of
like the gold standard for a psychedelic
chaplain role. And this is based on the
traditional chaplain role but with the
psychedelic training added in. Um for
those of you who aren't familiar, it's a
pretty rigorous um academic path. So it
starts with getting a degree um from an
accredited university um an MD um or an
MA in chapency or spiritual care. Um I
know some of us have you know degrees
maybe bachelor degrees or pieces of
paper from other organizations that give
us that sort of credibility in in doing
sort of or were or ordained ministers of
some organization or the other. The
chaplain role really requires you know
um a lot of places and hospitals require
you have an MD. Um and then there's that
layer of spiritual or psychedelic
specific education um which we u most of
us have done or are in the process of
doing. And this really goes into, you
know, ethical boundaries, um, set in
setting and hopefully, you know,
building in that spiritual assessment
and understanding, um, what happens from
a from a, um, biological perspective,
um, and understanding suggestability.
And then of course there's a supervised
practicum. This would include that real
world experience in a hospital uh,
paliotative care approved settings. And
this comes from the the the CPE uh or CP
sorry CPU um uh that you have to do to
get that experience. And then there's
board certification that comes along
with this role traditionally speaking.
And then there's this idea of mentorship
which is that ongoing education,
professional development, working in
teams, um understanding like learning
from somebody who's been in the field
for a long time. And I can tell you
these are all really um hard to get.
they take a long time and they are um
you know they cost some money.
Um
okay so then let's look at the training
gaps and there are many um so I guess
the question I've been having is like
are we prepared to place these
individuals into service today? Do we
have enough people with the right amount
of training? Um so there was some
research I found that was done um in
September that provides a really nice
analysis of about 13 um psychedelic
assisted training programs in the US and
it it it's trying to clarify how
organizations are preparing facilitators
you know what content they're including
where the gaps are especially in areas
like spiritual existential religious and
theological competencies and theert so
of course it's highlighting um a lot of
areas that need improvement such as you
know continuing education opportunities
for graduates It's um really
establishing parity across um physical,
mental and spiritual health within
psychedelic assisted care. Um and that
so like mental health clinicians would
gain that that basic competency in
spiritual health and spiritual health
providers would gain competency in
behavioral health. So that's what we
mean by parody. Um we're also really
needing that uh fieldwide standards for
training for these kind of providers.
also many active mentorship programs.
You know, I know that's something I was
really feeling a need for when I was a
chaplain for six months. I really was
trying to find a mentor and I I didn't
have one. And then clear guidance around
what the competencies really are. So, as
as I as I see it here, these gaps really
point to a discipline that's still in
formation. I mean, I guess I would say,
you know, we're we're building the plane
as we fly it. Um and many of us who are
looking to piece together our
competencies without a clear roadmap
really know this problem too well. So if
the goal is to work toward a mature
regulated field, how do we do this? And
that's what we I'm hoping to surface
here in this conversation um after this
presentation. Um I could see you know
building collaboration um with and
around this idea of spiritually
responsive care that requires multiple
rules that that could fill it. Um and we
also need to adapt to um scientific
developments, social developments,
regulatory and economic developments for
this field to mature. So what
traditionally was like a chaplain role,
you know, probably needs to mature and
kind of adapt a little bit to um this
need and these uh kind of emerging
standards.
Um so again, you know, as I as I was
talking to everyone about this, I think
a lot of us centered on this agreement
that um any early implementation
challenges in New Mexico would likely
require a more flexible hybrid and
phased approach to building out this
role. So as you see, you know, the
medical psilocybin act uh permits but
doesn't mandate spiritual care. So
there's an assumption that New Mexico
may lack sufficiently trained chaplain
statewide in early implementation in
these early days. So would um um a
phased compet competency based approach
work better? Um so we could anchor it
possibly in in clin clinician authored
care plans that specify spiritual health
functions. So in this initial framework
um the licensed clinician could retain
that responsibility and designate the
preparation journey and integration
roles per patient needs and those roles
could be the chaplain doula or
combination per availability and
competency. And one way I was thinking
through this more recently um is to how
could we automate some of the
matchmaking and team assembly to ensure
standards and adequate coverage. Um and
priority coverage would include you know
medical safety, psychological support,
uh spiritual distress, relational and
legacy concerns with clear escalation
pathways. So this is kind of a look at
the different phases of how this could
go. So phase one uh years one to three
would be um spiritual care competencies
prioritizing those competencies over the
fixed roles to ensure that we have
access while building capacity for
specialized care over time. Um and and
you can see then we move to you know
eventually to a full interdisciplinary
care model. So again, if we build this
that more phased flexible approach, we
could preserve the patient safety we
need and the ethical care it deserves
during a workforce buildout time where
we can maintain clinical accountability.
But again, as I mentioned here, we'll
have to provide some clear upgrade path
toward more robust interdisciplinary
care that supports the flexibility we
need while not abandoning spiritual
health as a core uh dimension of care.
Um, and one thing I I was thinking
through is um, if we rely on clinical
discretion alone in building out those
care teams, we might underidentify
spiritual or ex existential distress.
Um, and so we may not get, you know, the
full coverage of patient needs. So we
need the that explicit language,
standardized processes paired with the
right tools to ensure balanced care.
So these are some um, suggested pathways
to um, the practice. Um so you know we
just reviewed that you know gold
standard for psychedelic chaplain
training. So this part of the
presentation needs to consider how they
compare to other roles. And I think when
we hear from uh Daniela with the death
doula role we can start to kind of get a
better picture of this. This is just an
initial um uh slice. Um so you know
there are many death doulas and wellness
pro providers who may not hold you know
formal licenses but they do play really
distinct and valuable role and end roles
and end of life support um particularly
in providing that presence advocacy
guidance and continuity of care. So to
function safely within the psychedelic
assisted model, it would make sense for
uh these practitioners, doulas and uh
wellness practitioners, shaman,
community leaders, etc. to demonstrate
defined competencies appropriate to
their scope. And so again, we'd love to
hear from we'll hear from um that
community um in the next meeting, but
this is just a start. So this model I
have here considers cross competency.
again makes sense for mental health
clinicians to have some literacy in
spiritual and existential care and in
spiritual providers including chaplain
and doulas should demonstrate basic
competency in behavioral health, trauma
awareness and risk rec recognition.
So I mean what we want to do most at the
end of the day is ensure that the care
providers regardless of who they are
don't dismiss or misinterpret profound
experiences because that can um
undermine meaning making and negatively
impact patient well-being. So I'll just
take a moment so you can take a look at
this. So I have here the roles here. The
first one is kind of everybody in this
unlicensed realm. Um and then the
chaplain and then the license holder and
the foundational experience would be you
know end of life and sematic support
plus complimentary therap complimentary
therapies which most of them have. The
chaplain has the MD and board
certification and the license holder is
that you know making sure that there's
safety and they have the license. And
then we're looking at you know this this
buildout of relevant New Mexico line
training which has um psychedelics and
facilitation training peer support real
world experience with in-depth
recommendations group supervision
mentorship hospice pal of education and
then maybe like with the na nita or
equivalent exam completion on top. This
is just for everyone's consideration.
This isn't me telling you what to do but
I thought I'd build this out a little
bit. And then for the chaplain they
would need psychedelics and facilitation
training again peer support and
mentorship and then the license holder
you know has the psychedelics and
facilitation training me meaningful
pallet of care training of some sort and
that you know everything around being
them being responsible for safety.
Now, of course, when I mentioned before
like this kind of tiers of support, and
that's something we really need to
consider here, um because not every
person who qualifies for psilocybin
under the medical act may need this a
large expansive care team. So, I want to
show you a couple of examples of um
patient profiles and what service levels
might be appropriate. So I think work
would be likely need to be done to at
the outset to surface you know the
patient data individual needs and then
provider mapping to find a good match.
This is where a HIPACO compliant tool
that could automate some of this
decisioning with a human in loop could
be really um really valuable and I hope
we can explore it at some point. So, for
example, somebody who's been recently
diagnosed with cancer, who's a
nonpracticing Jew may have a support
option, appropriate support option would
be like a licensed therapist plus an say
an unlicensed wellness facilitator or
doula. And then up into somebody who's
medically complex, say latestage ALS and
identifies as a Baptist Christian, may
be best served by a physician or nurse
plus a chaplain. And again, you know,
this idea that we could automate some of
this with an intake tool that has
rules-based matching could right size
and right map support while ensuring um
adequate coverage.
So, back to this kind of general idea of
this um spiritual care roles. These are
some of the things that I think should
be part of this um providing again that
spiritual and existential support. um
using that non-directive listening uh
providing the legacy and life review and
then advocating for alignment between
their values and the care environment
and then participating as a member of
the care team.
Um so in the hospice setting um there
the chaplain traditional chaplain role
um one of the tools they use is that
spiritual assessment um and so I'm
proposing that the psychedelic chaplain
role would specifically be in charge of
this and this would be to really like
document the patients spiritual history
beliefs values existential concerns and
then identify spiritual or existential
distress relevant to um their psilocybin
assisted care. So this process could
occur during the early engagement phase
um in the preparation sess sessions um
and that precedes the dosing days or
like a week or so before. Um and these
frameworks here are used to solely guide
attentive listening and support ethical
presence and identify areas of ex
existential concern. are not used as
diagnostic tools and they reinforce the
role of the chaplain as specialists in
meaning making and spiritual care within
that interdisciplinary psychedelic end
of life setting. These are some of the
tools that are used. There's the ONC
framework. Um there's the SP facet and
the demoralization scale. And of course
these aren't mandatory. These are just
some of the tools that are used. And
these are some of the questions that
come up in the ONC framework. Um am I a
burden? Has my life mattered? Is there
unresolved connection? Is there fear of
non-being or loss of identity? And are
my beliefs being honored? So, you can
see how that's built out there.
And
this is um kind of a a patient journey
um example. So, this would be a proposed
care model in a diad format. So, say
with like a psychedelic chaplain or
eligible qualified doula and a licensed
facilitator. So there would be start
with an early engagement for with the
elig eligibility check and assessment.
Um and then there would be the
preparation day and then the dosing day
and then the integration
and this journey includes that early
engagement preparation sessions
medically supervised dosing integration
and these are the functions I sort of
built out here. So the medical risk
assessment would be done by the licensed
clinician. Um the psychological
screening by a l licensed clinician.
Meaning making and legacy death the
chaplain or death doula. Vigil presence
sacred witnessing done by the chaplain
or doula. And the clinical escalation
always by the clinician.
And these are some of the questions that
came up for me and I'm I'm hoping we can
address and maybe um we can sort of
document these or go through these. But
what came up for me was um that I wanted
to discuss with you all is how valuable
is spiritual care for end of life
vindications and does the current
language uh reflect that adequately
enough? And now we get into a question
of supply and demand. Um do we know um
what the pipeline is? Do we know how
many board certified chaplain there are
in New Mexico that who are interested in
psychedelic assisted care? Or do we know
how many uh unlicensed prov
practitioners we have? Um, should a
policy include a tiered model of support
based on degrees of end of life
situations? And then how can we ensure
the right level of care? Should the
definition broaden to include culturally
sourced spiritual caregivers and
community leaders? And should the
framework emphasize group supervision
specific to psychedelic uh spiritual
care?
So I wanted to um this is kind of the
this is the last um slide I have. Um so
new New Mexico's model I feel would be
best served by cross competency. Mental
health clinicians should possess
foundational literacy in spiritual and
existential care while spiritual care
providers including chaplins and doulas
must demonstrate basic competency in
behavioral health, trauma awareness and
risk recognition. Um and so I wanted to
just kind of talk about how do we get
there? So I wanted to show some of uh
the organizations institutions learning
and experience opportunities that are
building this learning pathway. And
again this is in a time where we don't
have standardized training for a
board-certified psychedelic chaplain or
even even doulas.
So I wanted to show you here. Okay. So
there's an organization called
transforming chapency psychedelics
network. Um then we have Harvard
Divinity School, Emory University,
Southwest College in Santa Fe, uh Nuropa
University, End of Life Psychedelic
Care, Congregation of Sacred Practices,
and then Modern Spirit. And again, none
of these are offering like psychedelic
chapency degrees, but I think they're at
the forefront of that that thought
leadership and start starting to build
out those experiential learning paths or
discussions, workshops, etc. So then
this could be helpful for folks who are
trying to get their continuing education
or just want to stay in tune with the
thought leaders and the opportunities to
learn. So um this is not really an
order. It's sort of an order. Um but
this is what's coming up uh that you
might want to plug into or explore. Um
first of all um March 26th Emory
University is having their uh science on
spiritual health symposium and this is
both virtual and in person. um Harvard
psychedelic intersections 2026 has a lot
of conversation on this topic uh that's
in April and then modern spirit um Joe
Tafur's organization
um has some opportunities for healthc
care providers coming up where they can
actually go and uh sit with um um sacred
medicine in Colombia um and there's two
groups coming up one in July one in
August and really the focus is on like
building that sort of interdisciplinary
awareness and helping healthcare
providers really understand the role of
plant medicine. And then there's another
organization that I've been hearing
about um called Congregation of Sacred
Practices. And mind you, I haven't
talked with them. I don't know a whole
lot, but I've just I've listened to a
couple of podcasts which intrigued me.
And they have a uh ministerial training
program um and they have an accredited
seminary um and they combine a lot of
like live training um a live community
and they do a lot of like swapping of
learning. So you sit for people, they
sit for you, and I think you they
require like several sessions of
sittings instead of like one retreat you
go to and maybe you'll do a psilocybin
sitting for one person. They make sure
you you get a lot of opportunities to do
it and they are completely um oriented
around spirituality. Um they're taking
applications for the fall. Again, I
haven't vetted them and checked them
out, but I I wanted to uh at least bring
that up. And of course, there's end of
life psychedelic care. Um, they have a
psychedelic core course that's underway.
Um, and there's a an end of life doula
training starting in May.
>> Hey, Jen, can I stop you real quick? Um,
I'm wondering if you and actually you
too, Larry, if you guys could turn off
like your camera video. I think that
might help cuz right now um the
presentation is just like a little
blurry. And I think if you both turn off
your like webcam cameras, it might
help the presentation be not as blurry
as often. Okay. I think
>> I think that'll help a little bit.
Thanks.
>> Okay. Okay. Great. All right. So, and
then um one thing I wanted to point out
there that end of life psychedelic care
uh started doing research um on death
work practices and I know Christine
Caldwell um unveiled some of her early
findings at uh the maps conference in
Denver in June um the first slice of it
and it looks like there's a webinar on
some of the more of the findings taking
place in February and I would highly
recommend everybody take a look at that.
I know it really helps me really
understand the practices in the field
kind of who's doing it um what kind of
care is provided and what just sort of
what's emerging in the field as a as a
standard of practice. So I I think
that's going to be really insightful too
and could probably help this
conversation.
Um and that's all I have and I'm sure
everybody else has more they want to add
but I just wanted to give kind of a
first glimpse of what's coming up um
where we could all sort of gather and
continue that learning and connection
building.
Um so I think we're getting to the end
of this presentation. Uh so the next
step for the committee is to explore
more accessible pathways to the
spiritual care role. Um for example,
could we build in can we um look at
opportunities for group supervision if
folks want to get more training um
without spending a ton of money or you
know seeking out programs here and
there? Could we build in some group
supervision opportunities? And then just
today actually um maps put out their
policy guide book and within it there is
an interaction there's a a section
called interactions with the existing
health care section health care system
section and I have a link to that here.
Um you could just go to I think to the
maps uh link and and find it. But this
has um uh a lot of references to New
Mexico versus Oregon and uh Colorado.
And I felt that after reading I felt
like I was really aligned with their
thinking and the folks that I that
helped me with this presentation seemed
to be aligned with it as well. So I
recommend everybody go and take a look.
>> Well, and sorry it's still kind of
blurry. If you could post that link in
the chat as well, that'd be super
helpful.
>> Yeah, I can do that as we're chatting.
Yeah. And that's really it. I think I
might have gotten through that a little
faster than I thought.
Jen, this is Larry. That That was great.
I've gotten like lots of gotten a lot of
texts and enthusiasm. That was a that
was a beautiful presentation. We all
thank you so much for doing that. Um um
I think if it's okay with you, we we can
open up the floor to to questions for
you.
>> Yeah. And if I can't answer any of these
questions, I'm sure there's somebody
else um in the conversation who probably
could. So, I would encourage other folks
to chime in as well.
And just so everybody knows, we've put
the information on how to raise your
hand and also how to unmute once we call
your name in the chat. And uh so if
you're interested or have any questions
or comments, please go ahead and raise
your hand at this time.
>> Thank you, Dominic. First up to speak is
Hannah Rose. Hannah, your microphone
credentials have been enabled. Go ahead
and unmute yourself whenever you're
ready, please.
>> Thank you. So nice to see um all these
beautiful faces again today. Um I am a
BW student here in Silver City, New
Mexico and a first generation kurandera.
Um thank you for this beautiful
presentation. Um some of my
thought processes as you were presenting
um were around your questions with
research around how many practitioners
do we have in New Mexico. So one of the
areas of social work um that we are
committed to in our code of ethics is um
research you know um researchbased
informed practice. And so I would like
to offer
my services as a volunteer um since I'm
not a licensed social work yet social
worker yet to support um gathering
um this research that it seems like we
need for this program.
I was on mute. Um, are you talking about
um collecting data on the whole gamut of
licensed and unlicensed potential
practitioners?
>> I'm I'm speaking to collecting data on
the unlicensed practitioners because I'd
like to support that. um that DEI, that
diversity, equity, and inclusion piece.
>> Yeah, that sounds like really
incredible, an incredible offer and
something that we absolutely need. So,
how can folks get in touch with you? How
can we um build that in to the next
phase?
Um, I can include my email and contact
uh information
um wherever it seems appropriate in the
chat however and people can reach out um
to me directly and then I can support
forming u a research team. Uh maybe that
means pulling in licensed social
workers. I mean, it most definitely
means that since I'm just a student um
and um and whomever else wants to be on
the team and then we could do um some
research and go through that process and
then I can um you know report back and
inform back to everyone.
>> Awesome. Thank you so much for the
offer.
You're so welcome. Thank you. And just
let me know where I should put my
contact info.
>> I mean, I think probably in the chat for
now.
Any other uh Larry, do you have any
suggestions on how we can stay connected
to this?
>> I would recommend Hannah, this is Jorge.
Uh just if you would leave your email in
the chat that would be great because we
also put that into the minutes as well.
That's captured in the minutes and the
minutes will also be posted. So probably
not your phone number uh and uh just
your just your email address would
suffice.
>> Thank you.
>> Next up is Chris. Chris, I've enabled
your microphone credentials. You may
unmute yourself whenever you're ready.
>> All right. Jen, that was fabulous. Thank
you so much. Um, I just wanted to share
uh a quick story. I was on the phone
this morning with Dr. Valerie Massuda.
She is one of the co-developers of Roots
to Thrive groups psilocybin therapy
model in Canada. And she's gone on to
develop her own more spiritually
oriented protocol. and and she was
saying something that I didn't I didn't
see captured um yet on your presentation
in terms of the the roles that a
chaplain could play and that is she said
we always take our participants through
a spiritual experience
before the psychedelic journey and what
she meant by that was uh a sound bath a
drumming um other contempl contemplative
practice ices because she says in order
to have a spiritual experience on
psychedelics, you need to have a
spiritual experience beforehand and it
really helps that individual let go and
embrace whatever shows up. So, I just
wanted to throw that out there.
>> I love it. Yeah, that really goes into
that realm of like experiential learning
and also how do you differentiate
between, you know, you don't always need
psychedelics to have a spiritual
experience,
right? And so, I think we need to ground
that ground that reality into something.
So, I love that. Thank you for bringing
that up and I know a lot of us have
opportunities to provide that for
others. So it' be good to like maybe we
we create that resource list too who's
offering those kind of experiences.
>> Thank you. Next up to speak is Kate.
Kate, I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself.
>> Hi everybody. Yeah, this is Kate Hawk.
I'm so glad we're all doing this. Thanks
for putting together so much there, Jen,
in such a nice organized way. I just
want to mention I'm doing a project to
map out all of the um everything I can
find that's happening in the world of
psychedelics and end of life and doing
interviews including some of the people
who are on this call. So, anybody I'll
put my email in the chat and anybody who
wants to uh get connected, I'd be happy
to uh talk with you and stay connected.
That's all.
>> Awesome.
Will you be publishing the results
somewhere
and making that available publicly?
>> Kate, your microphone is still enabled.
>> Oh, I got muted again. Okay. Yeah, I'll
be putting things on my website and um
we'll see. There may be a book here
sometime, but first it's it's just a
project that I'm going to put resources
on my website,
but I'll I'll put that in the chat.
>> Thank you so much, Kate.
Next up is James Brown. James, I've
enabled your microphone.
>> Hello, Jen. uh James Brown uh doctor of
pharmacy here in New Mexico. Um great
presentation. Thank you so much for
providing that information to us. And
and Larry, thank you for having her on.
Um my question revolves around set and
setting. When you think about the
chaplain and you think about the set
setting of death doulas and you guys
sitting in these spaces and the
container that it's going to be required
to to maintain, where do you see that
set and setting occurring? Do you see it
set and setting in a building, an actual
physical location, or do you also see
this set and setting at home? You know,
what are you guys going to be advocating
for? And what do you see that vision as
in that setting?
That's a great question and I mean I
think it's wherever the patient is most
comfortable and where they where they I
would make it a patient decision.
Hopefully there'll be be enough
flexibility for that. Um also when I was
thinking about the doula role I think um
when I had some doula training there was
a lot about creating the set in setting
and bringing in the flowers and like
making sure the environment is pushable
bringing in music and whatnot. So, I
think just it's it's yes, it's the wear
that's important because of
accessibility, but it's also the the
kind of content of the the setting
itself that I think is going to be
really important. So, I've I've heard of
people really doing a great job in
making a beautiful environment in a
hospital room if need be or in a in a
physical building, but I think it's it
it's going to depend on where the
patient can get to or where people can
get to the patient. So, but I think at
home is always a good a good a good idea
if the home is safe and clean and
whatnot and depending on what stage the
the patient is at.
Thank you, James. Thank you, Jen. Next
up to speak is Candy. Candy, I've
enabled your microphone. You may begin
when you're ready.
Just a friendly reminder, Candy, uh you
can tap on the microphone icon. That
will go ahead and unmute your uh mic so
you can speak.
So, what we're going to do, Candi, is
we're going to move on to the next uh
person in line. if you want to go ahead
and drop off back in. That usually
resolves most technical issues. Next up
is Jay. Jay, I've enabled your
microphone credentials. You may unmute
yourself whenever you're ready.
Okay. And just one more time, friendly
reminder folks, to unmute yourself on
the Teams app, simply click the mic
icon.
If that microphone icon is grayed out,
that may mean that your device is not
recognizing whatever you're utilizing
currently as a microphone. Please ensure
that that input is in place. And like I
said earlier, worst case scenario, you
may have to drop off the chat and then
drop back in.
At this point, next in line is Jamie.
Jamie, I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
>> Hi, Jen. It's nice to see you here.
Thank you for the presentation. Um, I'm
Jamie, a professional chaplain and
educator for chaplain and also um was
one of the founders of Nuropa
Psychedelic
um therapy program and um have
participated in this conversation about
psychedelic chapency.
I guess for for me the the challenge is
to really match the um care seeker or
who we might call the client or the
patient with the right practitioner or
practitioners
in a way that creates you know the
optimal conditions for access so that it
isn't expensive and it isn't um a burd
burdensome and it's also safe and so I'm
I'm I'm encouraged by this idea of a
research project to kind of look at
different competencies and how that
might match with different patient
populations.
I'm also curious um you know each one of
these groups is challenged in terms of
the experience that they would bring. So
a lot of professional chaplain would
perhaps not have much experience with
psychedelic medicines although some some
of us do but you know so that would be
the challenge and then um you know uh
physicians might have limited training
in spiritual care or even in paliative
care and so I think just commenting on
this uh this opportunity and challenge
and when it comes to the death duel as I
I'm curious you know how the death duel
And maybe we'll talk about this next
time, but how will they, you know,
obtain the kind of experience that they
would need in order to go into this
situation with such vulnerable folks
because most of the other practitioners
are able to, you know, accumulate these
hours and hours of um kind of supervised
time and where they're getting feedback
and can you just comment a little bit
give a little bit of a preview of this
how we how we might address this with
the death doula community perhaps some
others. you know, would would some of
the death duelas probably have have dual
kinds of um backgrounds. So, they might
be a nurse and a doula or maybe an
underground psychedelic practitioner and
a doula or some something that would
give that kind of experience with some
sort of mentorship.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, I'd love to hear from
others, but I mean there's been some
chat and discussion about a group, you
know, the group training um again that
apprenticeship and mentorship and all of
that, but that needs to be kind of built
in and there's got to be like a strict a
pathway like there has to be an offering
to be like, okay, here's a group
assembling. Everybody who wants to get
that, you know, to be eligible to serve
needs to have, you know, 12 hours or
whatnot. So, I think just getting really
formal about what that looks like would
be really helpful. I I'd love to hear
from others, too.
>> Yeah. I mean, my I guess just to throw
out my um concern is that the uh you
know, I I would want to see it more in
like the
uh 100 hours or something, you know,
more than more than 12. And for um
likewise for the for the chaplain or for
the other other providers, this kind of
uh the gaps and experience that we would
bring would would be important for all
the disciplines. So chaplain, you know,
I wouldn't want to see a chaplain just
take a a quick course in psychedelic
care and then jump into a situation
either with let's say they've never
experienced psychedelics themselves. So
these are just some of the challenges,
you know, um to make sure people have
enough supervised experience, enough
experience with the medicines that
they're sit that they're sitting for and
enough experience with paliative care.
So while there's still opportunities for
access, so I would suspect that having
having group opportunities would help
with access and also training. Perhaps
people could train in a group with other
practitioners present or something like
that. I'm not sure what the solution
would be.
>> Yeah. And as you brought up like what
what is that number of hours that
ensures competency and how do we measure
that? I think that's that's something
we're going to have to figure out.
What's the right number of hours that's
on par with other roles?
Is it 12 or is it 100
or something in between? Yeah, others
are coming up here.
>> Thank you, Jamie. Thank you. All right,
next up is Jay.
Jay, I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
Jay, just as a friendly reminder, please
ensure that you have selected the
microphone icon.
>> Unfortunately, we still can't hear you,
Jay. So, what we'll do is I'll next in
line to Chris.
Chris, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. go ahead and unmute
yourself, please.
>> Yeah, thank you. Yeah, I want to um just
to say a quick comment about the doula
versus the chaplain. In my experience,
doulas and chaplain do phenomenal work,
both of them. So, what we're really
talking about is appropriate training
and and so I think as long as both
receive appropriate training to work
with psychedelics, with people toward
the end of life, then I don't see any
distinction.
Thank you so much, Chris.
Next is Dr. Lita. Dr. Lita, I've enabled
your microphone. You may unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you so much for this present
presentation, Jen. This has been
amazing. And you know, having the lens
of spirituality going into psychedelic
care, I see that so valuable, especially
at the end of life. I'm also a hospice
physician.
Excuse me. and um and a program director
for the conscious physician psychedelics
academy. We're also a CMA accredited uh
organization through UNM school of
medicine and um the con conversation
around um having group you know we have
um 10 no 11 staff members from Red
Willow Hospice who are um part of this
cohort in our academy right now and two
of them are chaplain
uh and we're just you know there's just
such rich uh conversations and teachings
and yeah our program we're looking at
you know 50 or 60 uh hours of actual
dididactics and practicum and in-person
immersive and also mentorship and
following um others in the community who
are doing this work. So I think you know
it has to be um in my experience when
you have all those components in a
training program to be comprehensive um
and then we have you know a a monthlong
just talking about end of life though
this program is not just for end of life
care in fact Chris Caldwell is going to
be talking to our cohort as well um but
you know having
I'm a big fan of having a
multid-disciplinary group come together
and educate together because the wisdom
sharing is so beneficial amongst um all
professions. We have many physicians in
this group. We have therapists, social
workers, um again chaplain and um RNs,
NPs,
um which makes it much more rich than if
it was let's say just physicians, you
know. Um so thank you for this work and
um yeah, I think the hours you know I I
was thinking about that too. It's some
people come in with a very significant
psychedelic experience themselves and I
think that has to be counted in as where
is the individual in their own journey
with these um therapeutic medicines and
their own healing perhaps when they
start a program and um yeah anyways
things to figure out. Yeah, thank you so
much to learn about great to learn about
your program too, Lita.
>> Yeah, thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Lita.
>> And I see in the chat uh thank you Jay
for including that in the chat. For
whatever reason, the microphone wasn't
uh working for you, but yes, definitely
feel free to enter that in the chat as
that is monitored and minutes are being
taken. Next up is Hannah Rose. Hannah,
I've enabled your microphone. You may
unmute yourself when you're ready.
>> Thank you. so much. Um, Jen, I wanted to
respond to your question on how do we
measure um, how do we measure these
things? So, in social work, the way we
measure things is called smart goals.
And so,
um, we have, you know, it's specific,
measurable, timesensitive,
um, researchbased,
um, you know, all the things that go
with smart goals. So that's my answer to
your question on how do we measure this
and then um Dr.
Uh Lita um your question on
um your curiosity around
um people coming in excited, right? They
have lots of psychedelic experience. How
how do we make sure everybody is safe?
Um and so again in through a social work
lens the way we do this is through
grounded um practice which is um
research
based informed practice which means
experience right which which means we're
not going to negate these populations
coming in excited and and I um I believe
this is an opportunity then to take that
excitement with these populations and
say great you have all the psychedelic
experience, come into our program, do
the thing, and then they'll have to go
through their self-reflection, go
through their deconstructing,
internalized racism, prejudice, biases.
They'll they'll be forced to do their
own work, and it'll just filter out um
the the populations that, you know,
aren't quite ready in that moment. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Hannah. I appreciate that.
Next up is Candy. Candy, I've allowed
your microphone credentials. Please
unmute yourself whenever you're ready.
>> Okay, let's try this again. Hi
everybody. I'm Candy Worman and this is
my first time here. I live in Oregon.
I'm a board certified chaplain,
longtime hospice chaplain and been in
the psychedelic world and relocating to
New Mexico. So, I wanted to begin to get
involved and thank you so much, Jen, for
your extensive
presentation about spiritual care, about
chapency. And I so honor that at least
maybe it's a long-term goal to have the
interdisiplinary
approach. And I really appreciate the
discussion about
how are those that are not certified or
put differently um unlicensed
and don't have the depth of spiritual
experience
like a death doula
that to how to make that um a safe
practice, a safe presence. And then the
other piece that really hit me is in
that practice or in that teaching to be
able to also
teach what is their limitation of their
scope of practice so that one knows when
to call in a chaplain. You know, you
mentioned the non-practising Jew, but
for a chaplain to be present in that
psychedelic piece, they could have all
sorts of things come up that could have
meaning for them as a Jew. That's just
one example that really hit me. And um
I'm just really excited that this is
happening in New Mexico. And I've been
involved with Emory Transforming
Chapency Psychedelic Care Network. So,
I'm very excited to uh be involved and
it's lovely to meet all of you. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Candy.
At this point, there are no hands up, so
I pass it back to Jorge, Jen, and Dr.
Leman.
Oh, thanks everyone for all your
questions and and things you brought up.
There's a lot here and so I love that
we're all kind of digging into some of
these nuances.
>> Jen, that was a great talk. Everyone's
questions are really good, too. I mean,
I I do think we're kind of have a
several several kind of special
situations here in New Mexico that
really can allow us to move forward as
as leaders in this. Obviously, the the
bill itself um you know, the the Red
Willow team in uh TA has received, you
know, a grant for the GM model
psychedelic and um I know there's a few
people out. Does anyone from Red Willow
want to just mention a little bit about
your plans and your your program? I
think it would be interesting for
people.
>> Asher, are are you up? I see your
chaplain up there. Would you be able to
just share a little information about
that?
As sure your microphone is enabled. You
may unmute yourself whenever you're
ready.
While Asher's I'm getting her mic going,
you know, we had a com comment from Deb
Thorne about, you know, the sadness is
that there's, you know, you know, number
of people that are presented that are
interested in this care and that they
they likely won't be surviving to the
point in time when we move it forward.
Um I I think as we look at ways to
accelerate the you know the program um
from my perspective end of life is one
that could potentially be kind of first
in line for you know to get some pilots
going. The fact that um potentially can
be done at home. Um the um
I just think I I appreciate what you say
sort of the urgency of trying to make
this available to people as soon as
possible.
I'm thinking maybe Asher's not able to
uh not able to log on. Um Asher, I'm
definitely not the audiovisisual expert
here, but I I think um
some people have Looks like your your
mic is still off, you know, based on
there. So, there's a a button if you're
on your screen on the upper right for
the mic. If you click it, it should turn
on
and no worries if you can't connect.
Actually, maybe we can have somebody
from um you know, from Red Willow um
come to to a future meeting to you know,
to talk and present things.
I do want to mention if anyone has any
thoughts on other other areas to cover
in our inner self-education um um please
uh please send them to me. Looks like
Asher might Oh no, she's still muted
there.
>> Asher, how is this working?
>> Perfect.
>> Sorry about that everybody. Um
yeah um I am very new to Red Willow. So
I'll just speak briefly from what I know
that there um are chaplain and nurses
and physicians uh working with Dr. Lita
who's on the call here. Um and I do know
that we are also looking at doing
ketamine assisted psych psychedelic
therapy. Um, and yeah, we're just
working on getting people certified and
getting kind of training protocols in
place and just really staying up to date
on everything that's going on here to
try and be the front of the line to
offer um this medicine uh through
hospice. Um,
and
Yeah, that's that's about as much as I
know specifically. Maybe Dr. Leer would
be able to say some more as well, but
thank you for thank you for calling on
me here.
>> Thank you, Asher. Appreciate it.
>> Um, I had one other thought. This would
be for uh for Jen um or um maybe Jamie.
Is there some um
and this this may already be happening
but to to outreach to um chaplain in New
Mexico and you know potentially you know
do presentations and but that may all
already happen but I'm just thinking
about addressing what um I think Jamie
mentioned that many chaplain aren't
familiar with um psychedelic assisted
end of life care.
>> Yeah, I I was going to mention something
about that. Um, I started doing a little
bit of outreach to uh the hospice I
worked with um this year, this last
year, and I got some push back. Um, so I
I'm wondering if I went back if they
would it would be a little more open,
but the push back I got was we're not
doing anything unless our medical
supervisor wants us to do something. So,
I think I mentioned this in the last
call. I think doing some outreach to the
medical supervisors is kind of the first
step. Um, I'm actually going to reach
out to the other hospice in Sierra
County, um, and see if they would be
open to some kind of discussion and
communication around this. So, I'm going
to do it in my community and it might be
worth everybody kind of reaching out in
their county and doing something similar
and just spread this spread the task.
>> Yeah. You know, if it's helpful, um, I'm
going to volunteer and she's, uh, on the
call. either invite or myself I'm sure
be happy to just if you had like a
medical uh director that didn't have any
information and felt more comfortable
talking to a physician we could talk to
him send some information just put that
out
>> that would be fantastic okay thank you
>> so I wanted to bring up one issue that
I've been thinking about here which was
um um you know so we talk about the role
of you know of chaplain and death
doulas. But um you know how how will
that work in in are some of our native
communities? Is is that going to be like
a potentially a medicine person from one
of the PBLO, you know, for or from
today? So, um I was going to reach out
to a couple of people that I know from
those communities and um and see and uh
we've got the meeting going on, but no,
no, no. But they're doing all their
stuff and I
Um,
I will, you know, kind of reach out. I
think that would be good for us to
actually see if we can get some
viewpoints from the indigenous community
on how to how to do that. Um, Hana, I
know you're you're a Kurandera, so
that's um that may be relevant to you,
too.
And I've unmuted your microphone. I
mean, I've enabled your microphone. You
may
Thank you. Yeah. So, in social work
practice, this is where um a social
worker, a licensed social worker comes
in and can be a bridge to these um
marginalized populations. And so, um, I
obviously I'm highlighting just with my
presence the importance like the the not
only the importance of licensed social
workers involvement here, but um where I
I really am good at seeing where there's
gaps and how to fill those and um and so
this would be a way so get a social
worker, licensed social worker then to
reach out to um these tribal lands um
these ancestral
um populations and start to um do that
that work that that social work does so
well which is relating to marginalized
populations giving them a voice doing
whatever research is need you know we do
all that there's so many steps in social
work and so um you know we have six core
competencies our code of ethics is so
long you know and we go through all of
this slowly and we make sure we're we're
self-reflectction and we're combing make
sure we're combing through all of these
kind of check checkpoints, you know, and
then the first and foremost thing of our
practice is um client
self-determination. And so this would
kind of be like a little twist on that.
It would be self-determination for
marginalized populations um and cultural
sensitivities.
Thank you,
>> Larry. I saw that um Jamie Vichi had
raised her hand earlier.
Uh let me see.
I appreciate that. I've went ahead and
enabled your microphone credentials.
Then unmute yourself whenever you're
ready.
>> Oh, hi. Thanks, Jen. Yeah, for some
reason I'm not able to uh contribute to
the chat. I think it's my settings or
something. But I just wanted to say that
I'd be happy to um
uh contribute to some kind of a
educational um outreach to to spiritual
health you know practitioners in in the
state uh chaplain or other people who
are doing spiritual care as palative
clinicians you know like nurses or
social workers other practitioners. Um I
think that we could go through the uh
hospice organizations and maybe some of
the chapency like the chapency
certification groups and see if anyone
would be interested in um learning a
little bit more.
Thank you, Jame.
Any other questions? Uh, topics for
discussion or
>> Yeah, actually, I wanted to just bring
up um Red Willow's training program. Um,
I'm really curious if it would be an
offering they could roll out to others
or at least, you know, help kind of get
other hospices started. So, I think a
lot of them just don't know. They're
coming from like a they don't know where
to go. They don't know how to start this
whole thing. So almost like a um a rep a
replic replicable model and if they'll
be kind of putting together a
presentation or something like a how we
did it or how we're doing it and here's
what you should think about to help
other hospicees or is that in other
other um parts of the state not
competing with their territories.
I I I certainly don't want to speak for
them, but I I I do when I when I did
have some conversations. I think they're
still in the ramp up phase where they're
getting on-site training and getting
everyone sort of trained up. And I think
their grant is just starting here now.
So, I'm I have suspect it may take a
little bit of time before they're um
before they have something to share. But
it would be great to have like a model
in the state that's well known and get
that information out.
>> Dr. Lita,
>> your microphone credentials have been
enabled. You may unmute yourself
whenever you are ready.
>> Thank you so much. Yeah, you know,
regarding Red Red uh Willow, they don't
have a training program. They're going
through my training program with the
conscious physician psychedelics
academy.
um they're utilizing their psychedelic
grants that they received. Um and yes,
they have used ketamine in the past and
they just want to expand now that
psilocybin is on the table. Their
medical director and co-founder, you
know, both uh Joanna uh Hooper, Dr.
Hooper and Robin, they're very open to
bringing in other modalities and making
sure that they're just wonderful people
is really what it comes down to. And so,
yeah, they have a psychedelic grant that
they're utilizing to enroll their uh
staff into my conscious physicians
program. And um so yeah, our program is
ready to go for all of New Mexico. It's
a homegrown
um psychedelics program. It's been going
on for five years. You know, I've been
doing the research for over a decade. Um
and started conscious physician in 2020.
Then a few years later start started
training others. I trained other um
therapy groups in town of 20 plus
members and with great success um of
just education and um anyways it's been
really great. Um now this is a more
extensive program that I'm offering
that's a nine-month course. It's three
trimesters uh with um that's mimicking
human gestation. the first trimester
about self-care, self-compassion because
a lot of us in this field of not only
health care but also facilitation we get
burnt out just like the you know
unfortunately a recent news that we had
on the Iberane researcher renowned
Ibegan researcher in California who
committed suicide a physician and a
physician a day kills themselves. Um and
so uh remembering that we all need to
have very deep foundations of self-care
and self-compassion
before we can hold these spaces for
others. The second trimester is about
we're going to have a retreat that's
going to be in person immersive with
medicine with a third party involvement
with CPPA does not touch medicine. or
over the ground and um it's going to you
know be held outside of the state to
make sure u legality and um the second
trimester is all about integration for
three months and the third trimester is
mentorship apprenticeship and practicum
with other faculty in the state and
outside of the state because we have
people from all over the country who are
enrolled in a program. We have 27
members as we speak. Um, again, we're
we're going to be about we're going to
probably end up at 160 hours total of um
including both dididactic and um
nondidactic group sessions, small sess,
small group sessions, apprenticeships,
mentorships, practicum for
self-discovery, practicum for sitting
for others. Probably we're going to end
um end up at around 1605
hours or so. But that's kind of the
overview of our offering and um 16 out
of 24 of our guest faculty are New
Mexico residents. They're here. Majority
of our members who have signed up and
registered in New Mexico um and we take
really big pride in that. We have
indigenous um representation on our
guest faculty and facilitators as well
which we take big pride on as well. New
Mexicans, you know, um who are doing
this work, you know, and so um yeah,
that's about the program. I knew you you
guys were were asking about it. That's
why I'm sharing. Ask questions if you
have more. Thank you,
>> L. Thank you for giving us a summary of
the program. We appreciate it.
If we don't have anything else though,
we might be able to give people a little
time back. Um I just want to let people
know we do have um times that I put in
the chat for the next two meetings. We
have um um educational uh presentations
there from Daniellea Death Duel on the
committee and then James Brown. And then
I think at the next meeting we'll talk
talk about the idea of how to do um an
in-person blended meeting so we can you
know have some conversations in that
way.
any any other thoughts or comments or
anything before we um allow the
committee to sign off for the day,
>> Jen? Just amazing talk. I mean,
everyone's everyone's very much blown
away blown away with the depth of what
you shared. So, thanks again.
>> Thanks to you and thanks for everybody
who I was able to talk to in the weeks
uh coming up to this. It was really um
incredible.
All right. Well, we'll see everybody as
as many of you as possible hopefully
here at March 20th at the meeting where
uh Danielle is going to be uh
presenting. And I think it's really
helpful to get the different models. We
get the spiritual chaplain model, the
death doula uh model information about
hopefully you know get all this
information allow us to you know develop
our our recommendations.
Bye everybody.
Thank you everyone.